<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  S1000D Data Module Stub
  DMC: DMC-AMPEL360E-EWTW-070-000-00A-045A-D
  Info Code: 045 — Hybrid Operating Mode Description
  Topic: Hybrid Electric Architecture Overview
  Section: ATLAS 070-000 / 00A
  Programme: AMPEL360e Wide Tube-and-Wing Family (eWTW)
  Status: scaffold / placeholder
  Standard: S1000D Issue 4.2
  Note: Replace this scaffold with validated S1000D XML content before CSDB release.
-->
<dmodule xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.s1000d.org/S1000DIssue4.2/xml_schema_flat/descript.xsd">

  <identAndStatusSection>
    <dmAddress>
      <dmIdent>
        <dmCode
          modelIdentCode="AMPEL360E"
          systemDiffCode="EWTW"
          systemCode="070"
          subSystemCode="0"
          subSubSystemCode="0"
          assyCode="00"
          disassyCode="00"
          disassyCodeVariant="A"
          infoCode="045"
          infoCodeVariant="A"
          itemLocationCode="D"/>
        <issueInfo issueNumber="001" inWork="00"/>
        <language languageIsoCode="en" countryIsoCode="US"/>
      </dmIdent>

      <dmAddressItems>
        <issueDate year="2026" month="05" day="14"/>
        <dmTitle>
          <techName>Hybrid Electric Architecture Overview</techName>
          <infoName>Hybrid Operating Mode Description</infoName>
        </dmTitle>
      </dmAddressItems>
    </dmAddress>

    <dmStatus issueType="new">
      <security securityClassification="01"/>

      <responsiblePartnerCompany enterpriseCode="AMPEL">
        <enterpriseName>AMPEL / Q+</enterpriseName>
      </responsiblePartnerCompany>

      <originator enterpriseCode="AMPEL">
        <enterpriseName>AMPEL / Q+</enterpriseName>
      </originator>

      <applic>
        <displayText>
          <simplePara>AMPEL360E eWTW All Configurations</simplePara>
        </displayText>
      </applic>

      <brexDmRef>
        <dmRef>
          <dmRefIdent>
            <dmCode
              modelIdentCode="AMPEL360E"
              systemDiffCode="EWTW"
              systemCode="070"
              subSystemCode="0"
              subSubSystemCode="0"
              assyCode="00"
              disassyCode="00"
              disassyCodeVariant="A"
              infoCode="022"
              infoCodeVariant="A"
              itemLocationCode="D"/>
          </dmRefIdent>
        </dmRef>
      </brexDmRef>

      <qualityAssurance>
        <unverified/>
      </qualityAssurance>
    </dmStatus>
  </identAndStatusSection>

  <content>
    <description>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>General</title>
        <para>
          This data module gives the hybrid operating mode description for the
          Hybrid Electric Architecture Overview applicable to the AMPEL360E Wide
          Tube-and-Wing Family baseline.
        </para>
        <para>
          The module describes the top-level operating modes, transition logic,
          limitation principles, degraded-mode behaviour, safe-state philosophy,
          crew indication context, and maintenance reporting context associated
          with ATLAS 070-000 / 00A.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Operating Mode Scope</title>
        <para>
          The operating mode scope includes the controlled states used by the
          hybrid-electric architecture to manage energy availability, electrical
          distribution, propulsion drive operation, thermal capacity, protection
          functions, monitoring, maintenance reporting, and safe-state response.
        </para>
        <para>
          This module is descriptive only. It does not define final flight crew
          procedures, dispatch policy, minimum equipment list logic, certified
          mode transition thresholds, or detailed control laws. Those items
          shall be controlled by the applicable operations, certification,
          safety, control, and maintenance baselines.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Principal Operating Modes</title>
        <para>
          The hybrid-electric architecture uses the following principal
          operating modes:
        </para>
        <randomList>
          <listItem>
            <para>Off mode.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Standby mode.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Initialization mode.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Normal mode.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Monitored mode.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Limited mode.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Degraded mode.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Ground service mode.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Maintenance mode.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Safe-state mode.</para>
          </listItem>
        </randomList>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Off Mode</title>
        <para>
          Off mode is the condition in which the hybrid-electric propulsion
          architecture is not available for propulsion-energy transfer. Main
          propulsion energy paths are isolated or de-energized in accordance
          with the approved configuration.
        </para>
        <para>
          Residual energy, stored energy, control power, and maintenance access
          conditions shall be managed in accordance with the applicable safety,
          servicing, and maintenance procedures.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Standby Mode</title>
        <para>
          Standby mode is the condition in which selected control, monitoring,
          diagnostic, or support functions are available, but propulsion-energy
          flow is not commanded through the main propulsion path.
        </para>
        <para>
          Standby mode supports readiness monitoring, configuration checks,
          pre-operational status reporting, and controlled transition to
          initialization mode or safe-state mode.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Initialization Mode</title>
        <para>
          Initialization mode prepares the hybrid-electric architecture for
          normal operation. The system verifies configuration status, equipment
          availability, isolation state, thermal capacity, protection status,
          control communication, and monitoring function availability.
        </para>
        <para>
          Initialization shall complete only when the applicable readiness
          criteria are satisfied. Failed readiness checks shall generate the
          applicable indication, maintenance message, diagnostic record, or
          inhibition condition.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Normal Mode</title>
        <para>
          Normal mode is the operating condition in which energy source,
          conversion, electrical distribution, propulsion drive, thermal
          management, control, and monitoring functions operate within nominal
          architecture limits.
        </para>
        <para>
          In normal mode, commanded propulsion demand is accepted and processed
          within approved equipment limits, thermal limits, protection limits,
          and aircraft-level operating constraints.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Monitored Mode</title>
        <para>
          Monitored mode is the condition in which the architecture remains
          available but one or more parameters, equipment states, or diagnostic
          trends require increased supervision.
        </para>
        <para>
          Monitored mode may be entered after detection of a minor abnormal
          condition, reduced margin, intermittent status change, or maintenance
          trend. The mode does not necessarily reduce available propulsion
          function, but it shall increase reporting or surveillance as defined
          by the approved baseline.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Limited Mode</title>
        <para>
          Limited mode is the condition in which available propulsion energy,
          power, torque, thermal capacity, or system function is intentionally
          restricted to maintain operation within safe and controlled limits.
        </para>
        <para>
          Limited mode may be caused by reduced energy availability, reduced
          thermal capacity, protection coordination, degraded equipment status,
          or command authority limitation. The limitation shall be reported to
          the applicable indication, recording, maintenance, and diagnostic
          functions.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Degraded Mode</title>
        <para>
          Degraded mode is the condition in which the hybrid-electric
          architecture continues controlled operation after partial loss of
          function, equipment degradation, monitoring degradation, or detected
          abnormal condition.
        </para>
        <para>
          Degraded mode shall prevent uncontrolled fault propagation across
          energy source, electrical distribution, propulsion drive, thermal,
          control, and monitoring boundaries. Degraded operation may require
          reduced function, load shedding, increased reporting, dispatch
          limitation, or transition to safe-state mode.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Ground Service Mode</title>
        <para>
          Ground service mode supports ground-based servicing, inspection,
          configuration checks, energy path preparation, controlled diagnostic
          activities, and support equipment interaction when permitted by the
          approved aircraft configuration.
        </para>
        <para>
          Ground service mode shall preserve electrical safety, energy
          isolation, protection status, data integrity, configuration control,
          and maintenance traceability.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Maintenance Mode</title>
        <para>
          Maintenance mode supports controlled access to diagnostic information,
          built-in-test functions, configuration data, maintenance messages,
          equipment status, and ground support interfaces.
        </para>
        <para>
          Maintenance mode shall inhibit unsafe propulsion-energy transfer
          unless specifically authorized by an approved test or maintenance
          procedure. Maintenance access shall remain configuration-controlled
          and traceable.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Safe-State Mode</title>
        <para>
          Safe-state mode is the condition in which the architecture commands
          or maintains a controlled state intended to prevent unsafe energy
          transfer, uncontrolled propulsion output, thermal exceedance,
          electrical fault propagation, or uncontrolled system behaviour.
        </para>
        <para>
          Safe-state mode may include energy isolation, controlled shutdown,
          load removal, protection trip retention, degraded monitoring,
          maintenance message generation, and locked inhibition of further
          operation until approved recovery conditions are satisfied.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Mode Transition Philosophy</title>
        <para>
          Mode transitions shall be deterministic, traceable, and controlled by
          validated transition criteria. A transition shall occur only when the
          applicable command validity, equipment status, protection status,
          thermal status, energy availability, and monitoring criteria are
          satisfied.
        </para>
        <para>
          Invalid, incomplete, conflicting, or unsafe transition conditions shall
          be rejected, inhibited, or redirected to a controlled limited,
          degraded, or safe-state condition as defined by the approved system
          baseline.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Mode Transition Inputs</title>
        <para>
          Operating mode transition inputs may include aircraft-level command
          requests, propulsion demand, source availability, conversion status,
          electrical protection status, thermal capacity, equipment health,
          sensor validity, communication status, maintenance status, and
          detected abnormal conditions.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Mode Transition Outputs</title>
        <para>
          Operating mode transition outputs may include propulsion availability
          status, energy path enablement, contactor or isolation state,
          permitted power level, limitation state, crew indication, maintenance
          message, diagnostic record, protection status, and ground support
          access status.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Protection Effects on Operating Mode</title>
        <para>
          Protection functions may command or inhibit operating mode changes
          when abnormal electrical, thermal, propulsion-drive, control,
          monitoring, or communication conditions are detected.
        </para>
        <para>
          Protection effects may include load limitation, energy path isolation,
          drive inhibition, thermal limitation, controlled shutdown, safe-state
          transition, maintenance reporting, and retention of fault data for
          subsequent investigation.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Thermal Effects on Operating Mode</title>
        <para>
          Reduced thermal capacity or thermal exceedance may cause transition
          from normal mode to monitored, limited, degraded, or safe-state mode.
          Thermal status shall be considered when allocating propulsion power,
          permitting continued operation, or authorizing recovery.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Energy Availability Effects on Operating Mode</title>
        <para>
          Reduced energy source availability, conversion limitation, buffering
          limitation, or electrical distribution limitation may restrict the
          operating mode available to the architecture.
        </para>
        <para>
          The system shall report energy availability status and shall inhibit
          operating modes that require energy levels, conversion capability, or
          distribution capacity that are not available.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Crew Indication Context</title>
        <para>
          Operating mode status, limitation status, degraded status, and
          safe-state status shall be made available to the applicable crew
          indication and recording functions as required by the approved aircraft
          configuration.
        </para>
        <para>
          Detailed alerting logic, message text, crew action logic, and
          operational procedures are outside the scope of this data module and
          shall be controlled by the applicable operations and certification
          baseline.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Maintenance Reporting Context</title>
        <para>
          Operating mode changes, inhibited transitions, protection events,
          degraded function, safe-state entry, and failed readiness checks shall
          generate maintenance or diagnostic records as required by the approved
          maintenance reporting baseline.
        </para>
        <para>
          Corrective action references, fault isolation logic, dispatch effects,
          and return-to-service tests shall be defined in the applicable fault
          isolation and maintenance data modules.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Recovery Philosophy</title>
        <para>
          Recovery from limited, degraded, maintenance, or safe-state mode shall
          occur only when approved reset, inspection, readiness, or maintenance
          criteria are satisfied.
        </para>
        <para>
          Automatic recovery, crew-commanded recovery, maintenance-commanded
          recovery, and ground-support recovery shall be separately controlled
          by the approved system safety, control, operations, and maintenance
          baselines.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Operating Mode Boundaries</title>
        <para>
          This data module defines operating modes at architecture level only.
          It does not allocate certified thresholds, final annunciation text,
          failure probabilities, time limits, dispatch categories, control-law
          parameters, or maintenance task intervals.
        </para>
        <para>
          Those values shall be defined in controlled engineering datasets,
          safety assessment records, operational documentation, maintenance
          procedures, verification plans, and certification evidence.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Traceability Context</title>
        <para>
          This data module supports deterministic traceability between
          architecture-level operating mode definition, control logic,
          protection logic, S1000D CSDB descriptive content, maintenance
          reporting, safety assessment evidence, verification evidence, and
          lifecycle governance records.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Authoring Status</title>
        <para>
          This issue is an unverified scaffold. The content shall be completed,
          reviewed, and validated against the applicable BREX data module,
          business rules, applicability model, terminology rules, operating mode
          baseline, control baseline, interface control baseline, programme
          configuration baseline, safety assessment evidence, and verification
          records before CSDB release.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

    </description>
  </content>

</dmodule>
