<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  S1000D Data Module Stub
  DMC: DMC-AMPEL360E-EWTW-070-000-00A-046A-D
  Info Code: 046 — Redundancy and Degraded Mode Description
  Topic: Hybrid Electric Architecture Overview
  Section: ATLAS 070-000 / 00A
  Programme: AMPEL360e Wide Tube-and-Wing Family (eWTW)
  Status: scaffold / placeholder
  Standard: S1000D Issue 4.2
  Note: Replace this scaffold with validated S1000D XML content before CSDB release.
-->
<dmodule xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.s1000d.org/S1000DIssue4.2/xml_schema_flat/descript.xsd">

  <identAndStatusSection>
    <dmAddress>
      <dmIdent>
        <dmCode
          modelIdentCode="AMPEL360E"
          systemDiffCode="EWTW"
          systemCode="070"
          subSystemCode="0"
          subSubSystemCode="0"
          assyCode="00"
          disassyCode="00"
          disassyCodeVariant="A"
          infoCode="046"
          infoCodeVariant="A"
          itemLocationCode="D"/>
        <issueInfo issueNumber="001" inWork="00"/>
        <language languageIsoCode="en" countryIsoCode="US"/>
      </dmIdent>

      <dmAddressItems>
        <issueDate year="2026" month="05" day="14"/>
        <dmTitle>
          <techName>Hybrid Electric Architecture Overview</techName>
          <infoName>Redundancy and Degraded Mode Description</infoName>
        </dmTitle>
      </dmAddressItems>
    </dmAddress>

    <dmStatus issueType="new">
      <security securityClassification="01"/>

      <responsiblePartnerCompany enterpriseCode="AMPEL">
        <enterpriseName>AMPEL / Q+</enterpriseName>
      </responsiblePartnerCompany>

      <originator enterpriseCode="AMPEL">
        <enterpriseName>AMPEL / Q+</enterpriseName>
      </originator>

      <applic>
        <displayText>
          <simplePara>AMPEL360E eWTW All Configurations</simplePara>
        </displayText>
      </applic>

      <brexDmRef>
        <dmRef>
          <dmRefIdent>
            <dmCode
              modelIdentCode="AMPEL360E"
              systemDiffCode="EWTW"
              systemCode="070"
              subSystemCode="0"
              subSubSystemCode="0"
              assyCode="00"
              disassyCode="00"
              disassyCodeVariant="A"
              infoCode="022"
              infoCodeVariant="A"
              itemLocationCode="D"/>
          </dmRefIdent>
        </dmRef>
      </brexDmRef>

      <qualityAssurance>
        <unverified/>
      </qualityAssurance>
    </dmStatus>
  </identAndStatusSection>

  <content>
    <description>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>General</title>
        <para>
          This data module gives the redundancy and degraded mode description
          for the Hybrid Electric Architecture Overview applicable to the
          AMPEL360E Wide Tube-and-Wing Family baseline.
        </para>
        <para>
          The module describes the top-level redundancy philosophy, degraded
          operation principles, fault containment boundaries, availability
          management, safe-state transition logic, maintenance reporting
          context, and traceability context associated with ATLAS 070-000 / 00A.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Redundancy and Degraded Mode Scope</title>
        <para>
          The scope includes redundancy and degraded operation at architecture
          level for energy source interfaces, energy conversion equipment,
          electrical distribution paths, propulsion drive equipment, thermal
          management functions, control and monitoring functions, protection
          functions, and maintenance reporting interfaces.
        </para>
        <para>
          This data module is descriptive only. It does not define final system
          safety probabilities, dispatch categories, minimum equipment list
          provisions, certified failure thresholds, equipment qualification
          values, or detailed recovery procedures. Those items shall be
          controlled by the applicable safety, certification, operations,
          engineering, and maintenance baselines.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Redundancy Philosophy</title>
        <para>
          The redundancy philosophy is intended to maintain controlled
          hybrid-electric system behaviour after single equipment faults,
          partial loss of function, degraded monitoring, reduced thermal
          capacity, or reduced energy availability.
        </para>
        <para>
          Redundancy shall prevent uncontrolled propagation of faults across
          energy, electrical, propulsion drive, thermal, control, monitoring,
          and maintenance reporting boundaries.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Principal Redundancy Areas</title>
        <para>
          The hybrid-electric architecture may include redundancy provisions in
          the following areas:
        </para>
        <randomList>
          <listItem>
            <para>Energy source availability and isolation monitoring.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Energy conversion equipment availability.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Electrical distribution and protection paths.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Propulsion drive channels and local protection functions.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Thermal management and heat rejection capacity.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Control, monitoring, sensor, and communication functions.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Maintenance reporting and diagnostic data paths.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Safe-state command and inhibition functions.</para>
          </listItem>
        </randomList>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Energy Source Redundancy</title>
        <para>
          Energy source redundancy addresses the ability of the architecture to
          detect reduced source availability, isolate an affected source path,
          inhibit unavailable energy paths, and maintain controlled system
          behaviour with the remaining approved energy availability.
        </para>
        <para>
          Energy source redundancy does not imply continued full propulsion
          performance after source degradation unless explicitly authorized by
          the certified programme configuration.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Energy Conversion Redundancy</title>
        <para>
          Energy conversion redundancy addresses the ability to detect loss,
          limitation, or degradation of conversion equipment and to maintain a
          controlled operating condition through alternate conversion capacity,
          load limitation, equipment isolation, or safe-state transition.
        </para>
        <para>
          Conversion degradation shall be reported to the applicable control,
          indication, recording, diagnostic, and maintenance reporting
          functions.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Electrical Distribution Redundancy</title>
        <para>
          Electrical distribution redundancy addresses controlled routing,
          switching, protection, and isolation of electrical power paths after a
          detected abnormal condition.
        </para>
        <para>
          Distribution redundancy may include alternate feeds, segmented power
          paths, independent protection zones, contactor state monitoring,
          isolation logic, and fault containment boundaries as defined by the
          approved architecture baseline.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Propulsion Drive Redundancy</title>
        <para>
          Propulsion drive redundancy addresses the ability of the architecture
          to maintain controlled propulsive behaviour after degradation of drive
          electronics, electric machines, local sensors, local protection
          functions, or drive communication paths.
        </para>
        <para>
          Drive degradation may cause power limitation, channel isolation,
          increased monitoring, maintenance message generation, dispatch
          limitation, or transition to degraded or safe-state mode.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Thermal Management Redundancy</title>
        <para>
          Thermal management redundancy addresses the ability to maintain
          equipment temperatures within controlled limits after reduced cooling
          capacity, degraded heat transfer, reduced heat rejection, sensor
          degradation, or loss of a thermal control function.
        </para>
        <para>
          Reduced thermal redundancy may require propulsion energy limitation,
          increased thermal monitoring, load reduction, degraded-mode operation,
          or safe-state transition.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Control and Monitoring Redundancy</title>
        <para>
          Control and monitoring redundancy addresses the availability of valid
          command paths, sensor data, operating state data, protection status,
          communication paths, and diagnostic records required to maintain
          deterministic system behaviour.
        </para>
        <para>
          Loss of monitoring confidence shall be treated as a degradation when
          the system can no longer confirm required operating limits, isolation
          states, protection states, or equipment availability.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Protection Redundancy</title>
        <para>
          Protection redundancy addresses the ability to detect, isolate,
          limit, or shut down abnormal energy, electrical, thermal, propulsion
          drive, control, or communication conditions.
        </para>
        <para>
          Protection functions shall support fault containment, safe-state
          transition, inhibited restart, maintenance message generation, and
          retained diagnostic evidence as required by the approved safety
          baseline.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Degraded Mode Philosophy</title>
        <para>
          Degraded mode is a controlled operating condition entered after
          partial loss of function, reduced redundancy, reduced energy
          availability, reduced thermal capacity, equipment limitation,
          monitoring degradation, or detected abnormal condition.
        </para>
        <para>
          Degraded mode shall maintain deterministic behaviour, prevent
          uncontrolled fault propagation, and make the reduced system state
          available to crew indication, recording, maintenance, and diagnostic
          functions.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Degraded Mode Entry Conditions</title>
        <para>
          Degraded mode may be entered after detection of one or more of the
          following conditions:
        </para>
        <randomList>
          <listItem>
            <para>Loss or limitation of an energy source path.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Loss or limitation of energy conversion equipment.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Electrical distribution fault or protection trip.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Propulsion drive channel degradation.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Reduced thermal management capacity.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Sensor, control, monitoring, or communication degradation.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Maintenance-detected configuration or readiness mismatch.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Detected abnormal condition requiring controlled limitation.</para>
          </listItem>
        </randomList>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Degraded Mode Behaviour</title>
        <para>
          In degraded mode, the architecture may continue operation with
          reduced power, reduced propulsion availability, restricted energy
          paths, reduced thermal capacity, increased monitoring, limited control
          authority, or inhibited operating modes.
        </para>
        <para>
          Degraded mode behaviour shall remain predictable, bounded, traceable,
          and consistent with the approved safety assessment and certification
          baseline.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Fault Containment Boundaries</title>
        <para>
          Fault containment boundaries shall prevent local abnormal conditions
          from causing uncontrolled effects across adjacent energy, electrical,
          thermal, propulsion drive, control, or monitoring functions.
        </para>
        <para>
          Fault containment may include electrical isolation, load limitation,
          channel shutdown, thermal limitation, command inhibition, safe-state
          transition, maintenance reporting, and retained fault recording.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Load Shedding and Power Limitation</title>
        <para>
          Load shedding and power limitation functions may reduce propulsion
          energy demand, auxiliary load demand, or equipment operating level to
          maintain system operation within safe and controlled limits.
        </para>
        <para>
          Load shedding priorities, power limits, recovery criteria, and crew
          indication requirements shall be defined by the approved system
          control, safety, operations, and certification baselines.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Safe-State Transition</title>
        <para>
          Safe-state transition is commanded when the architecture can no
          longer maintain controlled operation within the approved degraded
          operating envelope.
        </para>
        <para>
          Safe-state transition may include energy path isolation, propulsion
          drive inhibition, protective shutdown, retained protection trip
          status, inhibited restart, maintenance message generation, and
          diagnostic data retention.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Recovery from Degraded Mode</title>
        <para>
          Recovery from degraded mode shall occur only when the applicable
          readiness checks, reset conditions, inspection results, maintenance
          actions, or ground support checks have satisfied the approved recovery
          criteria.
        </para>
        <para>
          Automatic recovery, crew-commanded recovery, maintenance-commanded
          recovery, and ground-support recovery shall be separately controlled
          by the approved safety, control, operations, and maintenance
          baselines.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Crew Indication Context</title>
        <para>
          Redundancy loss, degraded function, limited operation, inhibited
          transition, safe-state entry, and recovery status shall be made
          available to the applicable crew indication and recording functions as
          required by the approved aircraft configuration.
        </para>
        <para>
          Detailed alerting logic, annunciation text, crew action logic, and
          operational procedures are outside the scope of this data module.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Maintenance Reporting Context</title>
        <para>
          Redundancy loss, degraded operation, protection events, failed
          readiness checks, inhibited transitions, safe-state entries, and
          recovery attempts shall generate maintenance or diagnostic records as
          required by the approved maintenance reporting baseline.
        </para>
        <para>
          Fault isolation logic, corrective action references, dispatch effects,
          and return-to-service checks shall be specified in the applicable
          fault isolation and maintenance data modules.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Redundancy and Degraded Mode Boundaries</title>
        <para>
          This data module describes redundancy and degraded mode principles at
          architecture level only. It does not allocate certified redundancy
          levels, final failure probabilities, dispatch categories, time limits,
          equipment ratings, annunciation text, or maintenance task intervals.
        </para>
        <para>
          Those values shall be defined in controlled engineering datasets,
          safety assessment records, operational documentation, maintenance
          procedures, verification plans, and certification evidence.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Traceability Context</title>
        <para>
          This data module supports deterministic traceability between
          architecture-level redundancy definition, degraded-mode logic,
          protection logic, S1000D CSDB descriptive content, maintenance
          reporting, safety assessment evidence, verification evidence, and
          lifecycle governance records.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Authoring Status</title>
        <para>
          This issue is an unverified scaffold. The content shall be completed,
          reviewed, and validated against the applicable BREX data module,
          business rules, applicability model, terminology rules, redundancy
          baseline, degraded-mode baseline, control baseline, interface control
          baseline, programme configuration baseline, safety assessment
          evidence, and verification records before CSDB release.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

    </description>
  </content>

</dmodule>
