<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  S1000D Data Module Stub
  DMC: DMC-AMPEL360E-EWTW-070-000-00A-043A-D
  Info Code: 043 — Interface Description
  Topic: Hybrid Electric Architecture Overview
  Section: ATLAS 070-000 / 00A
  Programme: AMPEL360e Wide Tube-and-Wing Family (eWTW)
  Status: scaffold / placeholder
  Standard: S1000D Issue 4.2
  Note: Replace this scaffold with validated S1000D XML content before CSDB release.
-->
<dmodule xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.s1000d.org/S1000DIssue4.2/xml_schema_flat/descript.xsd">

  <identAndStatusSection>
    <dmAddress>
      <dmIdent>
        <dmCode
          modelIdentCode="AMPEL360E"
          systemDiffCode="EWTW"
          systemCode="070"
          subSystemCode="0"
          subSubSystemCode="0"
          assyCode="00"
          disassyCode="00"
          disassyCodeVariant="A"
          infoCode="043"
          infoCodeVariant="A"
          itemLocationCode="D"/>
        <issueInfo issueNumber="001" inWork="00"/>
        <language languageIsoCode="en" countryIsoCode="US"/>
      </dmIdent>

      <dmAddressItems>
        <issueDate year="2026" month="05" day="14"/>
        <dmTitle>
          <techName>Hybrid Electric Architecture Overview</techName>
          <infoName>Interface Description</infoName>
        </dmTitle>
      </dmAddressItems>
    </dmAddress>

    <dmStatus issueType="new">
      <security securityClassification="01"/>

      <responsiblePartnerCompany enterpriseCode="AMPEL">
        <enterpriseName>AMPEL / Q+</enterpriseName>
      </responsiblePartnerCompany>

      <originator enterpriseCode="AMPEL">
        <enterpriseName>AMPEL / Q+</enterpriseName>
      </originator>

      <applic>
        <displayText>
          <simplePara>AMPEL360E eWTW All Configurations</simplePara>
        </displayText>
      </applic>

      <brexDmRef>
        <dmRef>
          <dmRefIdent>
            <dmCode
              modelIdentCode="AMPEL360E"
              systemDiffCode="EWTW"
              systemCode="070"
              subSystemCode="0"
              subSubSystemCode="0"
              assyCode="00"
              disassyCode="00"
              disassyCodeVariant="A"
              infoCode="022"
              infoCodeVariant="A"
              itemLocationCode="D"/>
          </dmRefIdent>
        </dmRef>
      </brexDmRef>

      <qualityAssurance>
        <unverified/>
      </qualityAssurance>
    </dmStatus>
  </identAndStatusSection>

  <content>
    <description>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>General</title>
        <para>
          This data module gives the interface description for the Hybrid
          Electric Architecture Overview applicable to the AMPEL360E Wide
          Tube-and-Wing Family baseline.
        </para>
        <para>
          The module identifies the principal physical, electrical, thermal,
          control, monitoring, maintenance, and ground support interfaces
          associated with ATLAS 070-000 / 00A.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Interface Scope</title>
        <para>
          The interface scope includes the controlled boundaries between the
          hybrid-electric architecture and adjacent aircraft systems,
          subsystems, support equipment, diagnostic functions, and publication
          artefacts.
        </para>
        <para>
          This data module is descriptive only. It does not define detailed
          interface control drawings, wiring lists, connector pin allocations,
          software interface control documents, qualification procedures, or
          maintenance tasks. Those items shall be controlled by the applicable
          engineering, interface control, procedural, test, and fault isolation
          data modules.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Principal Interface Categories</title>
        <para>
          The hybrid-electric architecture has the following principal interface
          categories:
        </para>
        <randomList>
          <listItem>
            <para>Aircraft-level propulsion command interfaces.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Energy source and energy conversion interfaces.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Electrical power distribution and protection interfaces.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Propulsion drive and electric-machine interfaces.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Thermal management and heat rejection interfaces.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Control, monitoring, indication, and recording interfaces.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Central maintenance and diagnostic interfaces.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Ground support and service interfaces.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Installation, mounting, access, and structural support interfaces.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Safety, isolation, and protection interfaces.</para>
          </listItem>
        </randomList>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Aircraft-Level Propulsion Command Interface</title>
        <para>
          The aircraft-level propulsion command interface transfers commanded
          propulsion demand, operating mode requests, inhibit conditions,
          availability status, and protective limitation signals between the
          aircraft control functions and the hybrid-electric architecture.
        </para>
        <para>
          Command validity, authority allocation, failure response, and
          transition logic shall be defined by the approved aircraft control and
          propulsion control baseline.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Energy Source and Conversion Interface</title>
        <para>
          The energy source and conversion interface connects the
          hybrid-electric architecture to the applicable energy storage,
          conversion, conditioning, buffering, and isolation equipment.
        </para>
        <para>
          This interface includes readiness status, power availability, energy
          flow limits, protective trip status, isolation state, configuration
          status, and maintenance reporting provisions.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Electrical Power Distribution Interface</title>
        <para>
          The electrical power distribution interface routes controlled
          electrical power between energy conversion equipment, propulsion drive
          equipment, auxiliary hybrid-electric loads, protection equipment, and
          aircraft-level electrical systems.
        </para>
        <para>
          Interface control shall include voltage class, current limits,
          switching logic, protection coordination, fault containment,
          isolation state, and applicable electrical safety provisions.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Propulsion Drive Interface</title>
        <para>
          The propulsion drive interface connects the power distribution layer
          to the motor drive equipment, electric machines, local sensors,
          protection devices, cooling provisions, and propulsion control
          functions.
        </para>
        <para>
          This interface supports commanded torque or power delivery, motor
          status reporting, drive limitation, abnormal condition reporting, and
          controlled transition to limited, degraded, or safe-state operation.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Thermal Management Interface</title>
        <para>
          The thermal management interface transfers thermal loads, temperature
          data, coolant or heat-transfer status, heat rejection capacity,
          operating limits, and degradation information between hybrid-electric
          equipment and the aircraft thermal management functions.
        </para>
        <para>
          Thermal interface control shall support equipment protection,
          availability management, operating mode limitation, and maintenance
          reporting when thermal capacity is reduced or exceeded.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Control and Monitoring Interface</title>
        <para>
          The control and monitoring interface exchanges operating state,
          command validation, sensor data, equipment status, protection status,
          configuration data, and health-monitoring data between the
          hybrid-electric architecture and aircraft-level control and monitoring
          systems.
        </para>
        <para>
          The interface shall preserve deterministic state reporting,
          unambiguous mode indication, controlled fault propagation, and
          traceable diagnostic event recording.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Cockpit Indication and Recording Interface</title>
        <para>
          The cockpit indication and recording interface provides the flight
          crew and recording systems with controlled information related to
          hybrid-electric system availability, operating mode, limitation state,
          abnormal condition status, and applicable advisory or warning data.
        </para>
        <para>
          The detailed display logic, alerting logic, crew action logic, and
          recording requirements shall be controlled by the applicable aircraft
          indication, recording, operations, and certification baseline.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Central Maintenance Interface</title>
        <para>
          The central maintenance interface transfers fault messages,
          built-in-test results, configuration status, maintenance event data,
          diagnostic records, and corrective-action references between the
          hybrid-electric architecture and the aircraft maintenance systems.
        </para>
        <para>
          Fault code mapping, maintenance message priority, dispatch effect,
          and return-to-service logic shall be defined in the applicable fault
          isolation, maintenance, and operational data modules.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Ground Support Interface</title>
        <para>
          The ground support interface provides controlled access for
          maintenance diagnostics, software or configuration checks, test
          initiation, data download, and service support activities.
        </para>
        <para>
          Ground support access shall preserve electrical safety, system
          isolation, configuration control, cyber/data integrity, and
          maintenance traceability.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Installation and Structural Interface</title>
        <para>
          The installation and structural interface includes mounting points,
          equipment access zones, cable and conduit routing, cooling interface
          provisions, equipment clearance, maintainability access, and
          aircraft-level installation constraints.
        </para>
        <para>
          Structural load paths, vibration limits, access requirements, and
          environmental constraints shall be controlled by the applicable
          installation, structures, and equipment qualification baselines.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Safety and Isolation Interface</title>
        <para>
          The safety and isolation interface supports controlled isolation,
          interlock status, protective shutdown, fault containment, inhibit
          logic, safe-state transition, and maintenance safety provisions.
        </para>
        <para>
          Isolation states and protective responses shall be validated against
          the approved safety assessment, certification basis, maintenance
          procedures, and applicable operational constraints.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Interface Control Philosophy</title>
        <para>
          Each interface shall have a controlled source, destination, function,
          signal or power class, operating state dependency, failure effect,
          maintenance implication, and traceability reference.
        </para>
        <para>
          Interface changes shall be configuration-controlled and assessed for
          impact on safety, certification, maintainability, S1000D publication
          content, verification evidence, and lifecycle governance records.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Interface Boundaries</title>
        <para>
          This data module describes interface boundaries at architecture level.
          It does not allocate final connector identifiers, wire numbers,
          software message identifiers, installation drawing references, or test
          limits unless those values are provided by an approved engineering
          baseline.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Traceability Context</title>
        <para>
          This data module supports deterministic traceability between
          architecture-level interface definition, S1000D CSDB descriptive
          content, interface control records, maintenance reporting logic,
          safety assessment evidence, verification evidence, and lifecycle
          governance records.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Authoring Status</title>
        <para>
          This issue is an unverified scaffold. The content shall be completed,
          reviewed, and validated against the applicable BREX data module,
          business rules, applicability model, terminology rules, interface
          control baseline, programme configuration baseline, safety assessment
          evidence, and verification records before CSDB release.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

    </description>
  </content>

</dmodule>
