<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  S1000D Data Module Stub
  DMC: DMC-AMPEL360E-EWTW-070-000-00A-042A-D
  Info Code: 042 — Functional Description
  Topic: Hybrid Electric Architecture Overview
  Section: ATLAS 070-000 / 00A
  Programme: AMPEL360e Wide Tube-and-Wing Family (eWTW)
  Status: scaffold / placeholder
  Standard: S1000D Issue 4.2
  Note: Replace this scaffold with validated S1000D XML content before CSDB release.

  Suggested repository path:
  Programmes_example/090_AMPEL360e-Wide-Tube-and-Wing-Family/
  Q+ATLANTIDE_impact-study/
  000-099_ATLAS-impact-analysis/
  070-079_Propulsion-Eco-Tech-e-Hibrido-Electrica/
  S1000D-CSDB/DMC/
  DMC-AMPEL360E-EWTW-070-000/
  00A_Hybrid-Electric-Architecture-Overview/
  040_descriptive/
  DMC-AMPEL360E-EWTW-070-000-00A-042A-D_Functional-Description.xml
-->
<dmodule xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.s1000d.org/S1000DIssue4.2/xml_schema_flat/descript.xsd">

  <identAndStatusSection>
    <dmAddress>
      <dmIdent>
        <dmCode
          modelIdentCode="AMPEL360E"
          systemDiffCode="EWTW"
          systemCode="070"
          subSystemCode="0"
          subSubSystemCode="0"
          assyCode="00"
          disassyCode="00"
          disassyCodeVariant="A"
          infoCode="042"
          infoCodeVariant="A"
          itemLocationCode="D"/>
        <issueInfo issueNumber="001" inWork="00"/>
        <language languageIsoCode="en" countryIsoCode="US"/>
      </dmIdent>

      <dmAddressItems>
        <issueDate year="2026" month="05" day="14"/>
        <dmTitle>
          <techName>Hybrid Electric Architecture Overview</techName>
          <infoName>Functional Description</infoName>
        </dmTitle>
      </dmAddressItems>
    </dmAddress>

    <dmStatus issueType="new">
      <security securityClassification="01"/>

      <responsiblePartnerCompany enterpriseCode="AMPEL">
        <enterpriseName>AMPEL / Q+</enterpriseName>
      </responsiblePartnerCompany>

      <originator enterpriseCode="AMPEL">
        <enterpriseName>AMPEL / Q+</enterpriseName>
      </originator>

      <applic>
        <displayText>
          <simplePara>AMPEL360E eWTW All Configurations</simplePara>
        </displayText>
      </applic>

      <brexDmRef>
        <dmRef>
          <dmRefIdent>
            <dmCode
              modelIdentCode="AMPEL360E"
              systemDiffCode="EWTW"
              systemCode="070"
              subSystemCode="0"
              subSubSystemCode="0"
              assyCode="00"
              disassyCode="00"
              disassyCodeVariant="A"
              infoCode="022"
              infoCodeVariant="A"
              itemLocationCode="D"/>
          </dmRefIdent>
        </dmRef>
      </brexDmRef>

      <qualityAssurance>
        <unverified/>
      </qualityAssurance>
    </dmStatus>
  </identAndStatusSection>

  <content>
    <description>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>General</title>
        <para>
          This data module gives the functional description for the Hybrid
          Electric Architecture Overview applicable to the AMPEL360E Wide
          Tube-and-Wing Family baseline.
        </para>
        <para>
          The module describes the top-level functions performed by the
          hybrid-electric architecture, the functional relationships between
          major layers, the principal operating states, and the controlled
          functional boundaries applicable to ATLAS 070-000 / 00A.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Functional Scope</title>
        <para>
          The hybrid-electric architecture provides controlled propulsion-energy
          management, electrical power conversion and distribution, propulsion
          drive coordination, thermal-limit management, system monitoring,
          degraded-mode response, maintenance reporting, and ground support
          interfacing.
        </para>
        <para>
          This module is descriptive only. It does not provide maintenance
          procedures, servicing instructions, fault isolation tasks, operational
          checklists, or test procedures. Those subjects shall be defined in the
          applicable task, fault, test, and servicing data modules.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Primary Functions</title>
        <para>
          The architecture performs the following primary functions:
        </para>
        <randomList>
          <listItem>
            <para>Receive and validate aircraft-level propulsion-energy demand.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Manage energy source availability and conversion readiness.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Condition, route, isolate, and protect electrical power paths.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Command and supervise propulsion drive equipment.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Maintain electrical and thermal equipment within defined limits.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Monitor system health, configuration, and operating state.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Detect abnormal conditions and initiate protective responses.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Generate crew indications, maintenance messages, and diagnostic records.</para>
          </listItem>
        </randomList>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Energy Management Function</title>
        <para>
          The energy management function coordinates available propulsion energy
          with aircraft-level demand, system operating limits, equipment
          availability, thermal capacity, and degraded-mode constraints.
        </para>
        <para>
          This function supports controlled allocation of energy between
          conversion equipment, storage or buffer elements, propulsion drive
          equipment, and applicable auxiliary loads. The detailed allocation
          logic shall be defined by the applicable control and system design
          data modules.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Electrical Power Function</title>
        <para>
          The electrical power function conditions and distributes electrical
          power to the propulsion drive equipment and associated hybrid-electric
          loads. It provides switching, isolation, protection, current and
          voltage monitoring, and fault containment at the controlled
          architecture boundaries.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Propulsion Drive Function</title>
        <para>
          The propulsion drive function converts controlled electrical power
          into commanded propulsive output. It coordinates electric-machine
          operation, drive electronics, local sensors, protection functions,
          and interfaces to the propulsion control system.
        </para>
        <para>
          The function shall maintain controlled response to command inputs,
          equipment limits, detected faults, and system-level operating mode
          transitions.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Thermal Management Function</title>
        <para>
          The thermal management function removes, transports, rejects, or
          redistributes heat generated by energy conversion equipment,
          electrical distribution equipment, propulsion drive equipment, and
          associated control electronics.
        </para>
        <para>
          This function supports equipment protection, availability management,
          degraded-mode operation, and maintenance reporting when thermal limits
          are approached or exceeded.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Control Coordination Function</title>
        <para>
          The control coordination function manages state transitions between
          normal, monitored, limited, degraded, and safe-state operation. It
          arbitrates commands, validates system readiness, supervises protection
          thresholds, and coordinates responses across propulsion, electrical,
          thermal, and maintenance reporting functions.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Monitoring and Recording Function</title>
        <para>
          The monitoring and recording function collects equipment status,
          operating parameters, fault indications, configuration data, and
          diagnostic information from the hybrid-electric architecture.
        </para>
        <para>
          The function provides data to crew indication, aircraft recording,
          central maintenance, diagnostic, and ground support systems as
          applicable to the aircraft configuration.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Protection Function</title>
        <para>
          The protection function prevents uncontrolled propagation of faults
          across the hybrid-electric architecture. It supports detection,
          isolation, limitation, shutdown, safe-state transition, and maintenance
          reporting for abnormal electrical, thermal, propulsion-drive, or
          control conditions.
        </para>
        <para>
          Protection thresholds, response times, inhibit conditions, and
          reset logic shall be controlled by the applicable system safety,
          certification, control, and maintenance data modules.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Degraded-Mode Function</title>
        <para>
          The degraded-mode function maintains a controlled operating condition
          after detected equipment degradation, partial loss of function, or
          limited system availability. The function shall support continued safe
          operation, controlled load reduction, dispatch limitation, or safe-state
          transition as defined by the certified configuration.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Maintenance Reporting Function</title>
        <para>
          The maintenance reporting function generates maintenance messages,
          fault records, built-in-test results, configuration status, and
          diagnostic data for use by maintenance personnel and support systems.
        </para>
        <para>
          Fault isolation logic, maintenance message mapping, corrective action
          references, and return-to-service checks shall be specified in the
          applicable fault isolation and maintenance data modules.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Ground Support Function</title>
        <para>
          The ground support function provides controlled access to diagnostic,
          configuration, test, and maintenance support interfaces. Ground support
          interactions shall preserve system safety, electrical isolation,
          data integrity, and configuration traceability.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Functional Boundaries</title>
        <para>
          The functional boundary of this architecture is limited to the
          hybrid-electric propulsion-energy management, electrical distribution,
          propulsion drive, thermal management, monitoring, and maintenance
          support functions associated with ATLAS 070-000 / 00A.
        </para>
        <para>
          Aircraft-level flight control laws, cockpit procedures, detailed
          dispatch policy, hydrogen system detail design, and detailed
          certification means of compliance are outside the scope of this data
          module unless explicitly referenced by the approved programme baseline.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Traceability Context</title>
        <para>
          This data module supports traceability between top-level functional
          architecture, S1000D CSDB descriptive content, system interface
          definition, maintenance reporting logic, verification evidence, and
          lifecycle governance records.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Authoring Status</title>
        <para>
          This issue is an unverified scaffold. The content shall be completed,
          reviewed, and validated against the applicable BREX data module,
          business rules, applicability model, terminology rules, programme
          configuration baseline, safety assessment evidence, and verification
          records before CSDB release.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

    </description>
  </content>

</dmodule>>
