<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  S1000D Data Module Stub
  DMC: DMC-AMPEL360E-EWTW-070-000-00A-040A-D_System-Description
  Info Code: 040 — System Description
  Topic: Hybrid Electric Architecture Overview
  Section: ATLAS 070-000 / 00A
  Programme: AMPEL360e Wide Tube-and-Wing Family (eWTW)
  Status: scaffold / placeholder
  Standard: S1000D Issue 4.2
  Note: Replace this scaffold with validated S1000D XML content before CSDB release.
-->
<dmodule xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.s1000d.org/S1000DIssue4.2/xml_schema_flat/descript.xsd">

  <identAndStatusSection>
    <dmAddress>
      <dmIdent>
        <dmCode
          modelIdentCode="AMPEL360E"
          systemDiffCode="EWTW"
          systemCode="070"
          subSystemCode="0"
          subSubSystemCode="0"
          assyCode="00"
          disassyCode="00"
          disassyCodeVariant="A"
          infoCode="040"
          infoCodeVariant="A"
          itemLocationCode="D"/>
        <issueInfo issueNumber="001" inWork="00"/>
        <language languageIsoCode="en" countryIsoCode="US"/>
      </dmIdent>

      <dmAddressItems>
        <issueDate year="2026" month="05" day="14"/>
        <dmTitle>
          <techName>Hybrid Electric Architecture Overview</techName>
          <infoName>System Description</infoName>
        </dmTitle>
      </dmAddressItems>
    </dmAddress>

    <dmStatus issueType="new">
      <security securityClassification="01"/>

      <responsiblePartnerCompany enterpriseCode="AMPEL">
        <enterpriseName>AMPEL / Q+</enterpriseName>
      </responsiblePartnerCompany>

      <originator enterpriseCode="AMPEL">
        <enterpriseName>AMPEL / Q+</enterpriseName>
      </originator>

      <applic>
        <displayText>
          <simplePara>AMPEL360E eWTW All Configurations</simplePara>
        </displayText>
      </applic>

      <brexDmRef>
        <dmRef>
          <dmRefIdent>
            <dmCode
              modelIdentCode="AMPEL360E"
              systemDiffCode="EWTW"
              systemCode="070"
              subSystemCode="0"
              subSubSystemCode="0"
              assyCode="00"
              disassyCode="00"
              disassyCodeVariant="A"
              infoCode="022"
              infoCodeVariant="A"
              itemLocationCode="D"/>
          </dmRefIdent>
        </dmRef>
      </brexDmRef>

      <qualityAssurance>
        <unverified/>
      </qualityAssurance>
    </dmStatus>
  </identAndStatusSection>

  <content>
    <description>
      <levelledPara>
        <title>General</title>
        <para>
          This data module gives the system description for the hybrid-electric
          architecture overview applicable to the AMPEL360E Wide Tube-and-Wing
          Family baseline. The module identifies the architecture boundary,
          principal functions, major interfaces, and controlled traceability
          context for ATLAS 070-000 / 00A.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Architecture Boundary</title>
        <para>
          The hybrid-electric architecture overview covers the top-level
          arrangement of the propulsion energy conversion, electrical power
          distribution, thermal management, control, monitoring, and degraded-mode
          coordination functions associated with the AMPEL360E eWTW propulsion
          architecture.
        </para>
        <para>
          This module does not define detailed maintenance procedures, fault
          isolation logic, removal and installation steps, or functional test
          procedures. Those subjects are controlled by the applicable procedural,
          fault, and test data modules in the same S1000D-CSDB branch.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Principal Functions</title>
        <para>
          The architecture provides controlled conversion and distribution of
          propulsion energy, coordination of hybrid-electric operating modes,
          supervision of electrical and thermal limits, and interface control
          between propulsion equipment, aircraft-level power systems, monitoring
          systems, and maintenance support systems.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Major System Interfaces</title>
        <para>
          The architecture interfaces with the aircraft electrical power system,
          propulsion control system, energy storage or energy conversion
          equipment, thermal management system, cockpit indication and recording
          functions, central maintenance functions, and applicable ground support
          and diagnostic interfaces.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Operating Modes</title>
        <para>
          The architecture supports normal, monitored, limited, and degraded
          operating modes. Mode transition logic, protection thresholds, crew
          indication, dispatch implications, and maintenance reporting shall be
          defined in the applicable control, monitoring, fault isolation, and
          operational data modules.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Traceability Context</title>
        <para>
          This data module is part of the ATLAS 070-079 Propulsion Eco-Tech and
          Hybrid-Electric branch. It is intended to support deterministic
          traceability between architecture definition, S1000D publication
          artefacts, system interfaces, verification evidence, and lifecycle
          governance records.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Authoring Status</title>
        <para>
          This issue is an unverified scaffold. The content shall be reviewed,
          completed, and validated against the applicable BREX, business rules,
          applicability model, terminology rules, and programme configuration
          baseline before publication or CSDB release.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>
    </description>
  </content>

</dmodule>
