<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  S1000D Data Module Stub
  DMC: DMC-AMPEL360E-EWTW-070-000-00A-044A-D
  Info Code: 044 — Energy Flow Description
  Topic: Hybrid Electric Architecture Overview
  Section: ATLAS 070-000 / 00A
  Programme: AMPEL360e Wide Tube-and-Wing Family (eWTW)
  Status: scaffold / placeholder
  Standard: S1000D Issue 4.2
  Note: Replace this scaffold with validated S1000D XML content before CSDB release.
-->
<dmodule xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.s1000d.org/S1000DIssue4.2/xml_schema_flat/descript.xsd">

  <identAndStatusSection>
    <dmAddress>
      <dmIdent>
        <dmCode
          modelIdentCode="AMPEL360E"
          systemDiffCode="EWTW"
          systemCode="070"
          subSystemCode="0"
          subSubSystemCode="0"
          assyCode="00"
          disassyCode="00"
          disassyCodeVariant="A"
          infoCode="044"
          infoCodeVariant="A"
          itemLocationCode="D"/>
        <issueInfo issueNumber="001" inWork="00"/>
        <language languageIsoCode="en" countryIsoCode="US"/>
      </dmIdent>

      <dmAddressItems>
        <issueDate year="2026" month="05" day="14"/>
        <dmTitle>
          <techName>Hybrid Electric Architecture Overview</techName>
          <infoName>Energy Flow Description</infoName>
        </dmTitle>
      </dmAddressItems>
    </dmAddress>

    <dmStatus issueType="new">
      <security securityClassification="01"/>

      <responsiblePartnerCompany enterpriseCode="AMPEL">
        <enterpriseName>AMPEL / Q+</enterpriseName>
      </responsiblePartnerCompany>

      <originator enterpriseCode="AMPEL">
        <enterpriseName>AMPEL / Q+</enterpriseName>
      </originator>

      <applic>
        <displayText>
          <simplePara>AMPEL360E eWTW All Configurations</simplePara>
        </displayText>
      </applic>

      <brexDmRef>
        <dmRef>
          <dmRefIdent>
            <dmCode
              modelIdentCode="AMPEL360E"
              systemDiffCode="EWTW"
              systemCode="070"
              subSystemCode="0"
              subSubSystemCode="0"
              assyCode="00"
              disassyCode="00"
              disassyCodeVariant="A"
              infoCode="022"
              infoCodeVariant="A"
              itemLocationCode="D"/>
          </dmRefIdent>
        </dmRef>
      </brexDmRef>

      <qualityAssurance>
        <unverified/>
      </qualityAssurance>
    </dmStatus>
  </identAndStatusSection>

  <content>
    <description>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>General</title>
        <para>
          This data module gives the energy flow description for the Hybrid
          Electric Architecture Overview applicable to the AMPEL360E Wide
          Tube-and-Wing Family baseline.
        </para>
        <para>
          The module describes the top-level energy paths, conversion stages,
          distribution paths, thermal energy removal paths, monitoring points,
          and protection boundaries associated with ATLAS 070-000 / 00A.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Energy Flow Scope</title>
        <para>
          The energy flow scope includes the controlled movement of energy from
          the aircraft-level energy source or conversion equipment through the
          hybrid-electric power architecture to the propulsion drive equipment
          and associated support functions.
        </para>
        <para>
          This module is descriptive only. It does not define final load
          calculations, detailed wiring schedules, equipment ratings, protection
          settings, thermal sizing, or certified performance limits. Those
          values shall be controlled by the applicable engineering, safety,
          certification, and verification baselines.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Principal Energy Flow Paths</title>
        <para>
          The hybrid-electric architecture contains the following principal
          energy flow paths:
        </para>
        <randomList>
          <listItem>
            <para>Primary energy source to energy conversion equipment.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Energy conversion equipment to electrical conditioning equipment.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Electrical conditioning equipment to distribution and protection equipment.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Distribution and protection equipment to propulsion drive equipment.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Propulsion drive equipment to electric machines or propulsive devices.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Electrical and conversion losses to thermal management equipment.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Thermal management equipment to heat rejection or redistribution interfaces.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Monitoring and diagnostic data flow to aircraft indication, recording, and maintenance systems.</para>
          </listItem>
        </randomList>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Primary Energy Input</title>
        <para>
          The primary energy input function supplies available energy to the
          hybrid-electric architecture in accordance with the applicable aircraft
          configuration. The energy source may be connected to conversion,
          conditioning, buffering, isolation, and protection equipment before
          energy is made available to the propulsion power path.
        </para>
        <para>
          Energy input availability, source readiness, isolation state, and
          protective status shall be monitored and reported to the applicable
          control, indication, and maintenance functions.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Energy Conversion Flow</title>
        <para>
          The energy conversion flow transforms source energy into controlled
          electrical power suitable for the hybrid-electric propulsion
          architecture. The conversion stage may include conversion equipment,
          control electronics, contactors, protection devices, sensors, and
          local cooling provisions.
        </para>
        <para>
          Conversion flow shall remain within the operating limits defined by
          the approved system configuration, equipment qualification baseline,
          thermal capacity, and safety assessment evidence.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Electrical Conditioning Flow</title>
        <para>
          The electrical conditioning flow stabilizes, regulates, or adapts
          electrical power before distribution to propulsion and associated
          hybrid-electric loads. This flow may include voltage control, current
          limitation, filtering, switching, isolation, and protection functions.
        </para>
        <para>
          Conditioning functions shall support controlled response to transient
          demand, abnormal electrical conditions, degraded equipment
          availability, and commanded mode transitions.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Distribution and Protection Flow</title>
        <para>
          The distribution and protection flow routes controlled electrical
          energy from the conditioning equipment to the propulsion drive
          equipment and applicable auxiliary hybrid-electric loads.
        </para>
        <para>
          The distribution path shall include controlled switching, isolation,
          fault containment, protection coordination, status monitoring, and
          maintenance reporting provisions.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Propulsion Drive Energy Flow</title>
        <para>
          The propulsion drive energy flow transfers controlled electrical power
          to motor drive equipment and electric machines. The drive equipment
          converts the electrical energy into commanded mechanical or propulsive
          output in accordance with aircraft-level propulsion demand and local
          equipment limits.
        </para>
        <para>
          The propulsion drive energy flow shall be monitored for availability,
          commanded output, limitation state, protection status, and abnormal
          operating conditions.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Auxiliary and Buffer Energy Flow</title>
        <para>
          Auxiliary and buffer energy flow supports transient management,
          equipment protection, control power supply, limited non-mission
          buffering, and safe transition between operating states where
          applicable to the approved configuration.
        </para>
        <para>
          Buffer energy shall not be treated as the primary mission energy
          source unless explicitly authorized by the certified programme
          baseline.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Thermal Energy Flow</title>
        <para>
          Thermal energy flow is generated by conversion losses, electrical
          distribution losses, drive equipment losses, control electronics, and
          associated auxiliary equipment.
        </para>
        <para>
          The thermal management function collects, transports, rejects, or
          redistributes this thermal energy to maintain equipment operation
          within defined temperature limits.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Heat Rejection Flow</title>
        <para>
          Heat rejection flow transfers thermal energy from hybrid-electric
          equipment to the applicable aircraft heat rejection or redistribution
          interfaces. The available heat rejection capacity may limit propulsion
          energy flow, equipment availability, or operating mode.
        </para>
        <para>
          Reduced thermal capacity shall be reported to the control and
          maintenance functions and may cause limitation, degraded operation, or
          safe-state transition.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Energy Flow Monitoring</title>
        <para>
          Energy flow monitoring provides controlled measurement or status
          reporting for source availability, conversion status, voltage, current,
          power, temperature, isolation state, protection state, and equipment
          health.
        </para>
        <para>
          Monitoring data shall support flight crew indication, aircraft
          recording, central maintenance reporting, diagnostics, fault
          isolation, verification evidence, and lifecycle traceability.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Abnormal Energy Flow Conditions</title>
        <para>
          Abnormal energy flow conditions include loss of source availability,
          conversion limitation, over-current, over-voltage, under-voltage,
          isolation fault, thermal exceedance, drive limitation, protection
          trip, communication loss, or degraded monitoring capability.
        </para>
        <para>
          Abnormal conditions shall be detected, isolated, limited, reported,
          and managed in accordance with the approved control, safety,
          certification, and maintenance baselines.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Energy Flow Protection Philosophy</title>
        <para>
          The protection philosophy shall prevent uncontrolled propagation of
          electrical, thermal, or control faults through the hybrid-electric
          energy path.
        </para>
        <para>
          Protection functions shall support controlled isolation, load
          limitation, protective shutdown, safe-state transition, maintenance
          message generation, and traceable fault recording.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Operating Mode Effects on Energy Flow</title>
        <para>
          The energy flow path changes according to operating mode. Normal mode
          permits controlled energy flow within nominal limits. Monitored mode
          increases supervision or reporting. Limited mode restricts available
          power or load allocation. Degraded mode maintains controlled operation
          with reduced function. Safe-state mode isolates or removes energy flow
          as required to preserve safety.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Energy Flow Boundaries</title>
        <para>
          This data module describes energy flow at architecture level only.
          It does not allocate final power ratings, cable sizing, protection
          thresholds, cooling capacities, heat exchanger ratings, dispatch
          limits, or certified performance values.
        </para>
        <para>
          Those values shall be defined in controlled engineering datasets,
          interface control records, verification plans, equipment
          qualification data, and certification evidence.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Traceability Context</title>
        <para>
          This data module supports deterministic traceability between
          architecture-level energy flow definition, hybrid-electric system
          interfaces, S1000D CSDB descriptive content, safety assessment
          evidence, verification evidence, maintenance reporting, and lifecycle
          governance records.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Authoring Status</title>
        <para>
          This issue is an unverified scaffold. The content shall be completed,
          reviewed, and validated against the applicable BREX data module,
          business rules, applicability model, terminology rules, energy flow
          baseline, interface control baseline, programme configuration
          baseline, safety assessment evidence, and verification records before
          CSDB release.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

    </description>
  </content>

</dmodule>
