<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  S1000D Data Module Stub
  DMC: DMC-AMPEL360E-EWTW-070-000-00A-041A-D
  Info Code: 041 — System Architecture Overview
  Topic: Hybrid Electric Architecture Overview
  Section: ATLAS 070-000 / 00A
  Programme: AMPEL360e Wide Tube-and-Wing Family (eWTW)
  Status: scaffold / placeholder
  Standard: S1000D Issue 4.2
  Note: Replace this scaffold with validated S1000D XML content before CSDB release.

  Suggested repository path:
  Programmes_example/090_AMPEL360e-Wide-Tube-and-Wing-Family/
  Q+ATLANTIDE_impact-study/
  000-099_ATLAS-impact-analysis/
  070-079_Propulsion-Eco-Tech-e-Hibrido-Electrica/
  S1000D-CSDB/DMC/
  DMC-AMPEL360E-EWTW-070-000/
  00A_Hybrid-Electric-Architecture-Overview/
  040_descriptive/
  DMC-AMPEL360E-EWTW-070-000-00A-041A-D_System-Architecture-Overview.xml
-->
<dmodule xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.s1000d.org/S1000DIssue4.2/xml_schema_flat/descript.xsd">

  <identAndStatusSection>
    <dmAddress>
      <dmIdent>
        <dmCode
          modelIdentCode="AMPEL360E"
          systemDiffCode="EWTW"
          systemCode="070"
          subSystemCode="0"
          subSubSystemCode="0"
          assyCode="00"
          disassyCode="00"
          disassyCodeVariant="A"
          infoCode="041"
          infoCodeVariant="A"
          itemLocationCode="D"/>
        <issueInfo issueNumber="001" inWork="00"/>
        <language languageIsoCode="en" countryIsoCode="US"/>
      </dmIdent>

      <dmAddressItems>
        <issueDate year="2026" month="05" day="14"/>
        <dmTitle>
          <techName>Hybrid Electric Architecture Overview</techName>
          <infoName>System Architecture Overview</infoName>
        </dmTitle>
      </dmAddressItems>
    </dmAddress>

    <dmStatus issueType="new">
      <security securityClassification="01"/>

      <responsiblePartnerCompany enterpriseCode="AMPEL">
        <enterpriseName>AMPEL / Q+</enterpriseName>
      </responsiblePartnerCompany>

      <originator enterpriseCode="AMPEL">
        <enterpriseName>AMPEL / Q+</enterpriseName>
      </originator>

      <applic>
        <displayText>
          <simplePara>AMPEL360E eWTW All Configurations</simplePara>
        </displayText>
      </applic>

      <brexDmRef>
        <dmRef>
          <dmRefIdent>
            <dmCode
              modelIdentCode="AMPEL360E"
              systemDiffCode="EWTW"
              systemCode="070"
              subSystemCode="0"
              subSubSystemCode="0"
              assyCode="00"
              disassyCode="00"
              disassyCodeVariant="A"
              infoCode="022"
              infoCodeVariant="A"
              itemLocationCode="D"/>
          </dmRefIdent>
        </dmRef>
      </brexDmRef>

      <qualityAssurance>
        <unverified/>
      </qualityAssurance>
    </dmStatus>
  </identAndStatusSection>

  <content>
    <description>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>General</title>
        <para>
          This data module gives the system architecture overview for the
          Hybrid Electric Architecture Overview applicable to the AMPEL360E
          Wide Tube-and-Wing Family baseline.
        </para>
        <para>
          The module identifies the top-level architectural arrangement,
          functional layers, principal system interfaces, control boundaries,
          monitoring provisions, and traceability context for ATLAS 070-000 /
          00A.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Architecture Scope</title>
        <para>
          The hybrid-electric architecture includes the aircraft-level
          arrangement of energy conversion, electrical power distribution,
          propulsion drive equipment, thermal management, control and
          monitoring functions, maintenance interfaces, and degraded-mode
          coordination logic.
        </para>
        <para>
          This module is architecture-descriptive only. It does not provide
          removal, installation, servicing, operational, or troubleshooting
          procedures. Those subjects shall be defined in the applicable
          procedural, servicing, fault isolation, and test data modules.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Architectural Layers</title>
        <para>
          The system architecture is organized into the following controlled
          functional layers:
        </para>
        <randomList>
          <listItem>
            <para>Energy source and conversion layer.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Electrical distribution and protection layer.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Propulsion drive and actuation layer.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Thermal management and heat rejection layer.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Control, monitoring, indication, and recording layer.</para>
          </listItem>
          <listItem>
            <para>Maintenance, diagnostics, and ground support interface layer.</para>
          </listItem>
        </randomList>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Energy Source and Conversion Layer</title>
        <para>
          The energy source and conversion layer provides the controlled supply
          of propulsion energy to the hybrid-electric architecture. Depending on
          the applicable programme configuration, this layer may include energy
          storage equipment, fuel-cell or other conversion equipment, auxiliary
          buffering equipment, contactors, isolation devices, and energy
          conditioning functions.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Electrical Distribution and Protection Layer</title>
        <para>
          The electrical distribution and protection layer routes electrical
          power between the energy conversion equipment, propulsion drive
          equipment, aircraft electrical loads, and applicable auxiliary
          systems. This layer includes protection, isolation, switching,
          monitoring, and fault containment functions.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Propulsion Drive Layer</title>
        <para>
          The propulsion drive layer converts controlled electrical power into
          propulsive mechanical output. It includes motor drive equipment,
          electric machines, associated control electronics, local sensors,
          protection functions, and interfaces to the propulsion control system.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Thermal Management Layer</title>
        <para>
          The thermal management layer maintains the temperature of
          hybrid-electric equipment within defined operating limits. It includes
          heat acquisition, transfer, rejection, monitoring, and control
          functions associated with energy conversion equipment, electrical
          distribution equipment, propulsion drive equipment, and applicable
          aircraft thermal interfaces.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Control and Monitoring Layer</title>
        <para>
          The control and monitoring layer coordinates system operating modes,
          supervises limits, records health data, provides crew and maintenance
          indications, and supports protective responses to abnormal conditions.
          This layer interfaces with aircraft-level control, indication,
          recording, central maintenance, and diagnostic systems.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Maintenance and Ground Support Layer</title>
        <para>
          The maintenance and ground support layer provides access to diagnostic
          information, configuration data, built-in-test results, fault records,
          maintenance messages, and controlled ground support interfaces. The
          detailed maintenance logic shall be defined in the applicable
          maintenance, fault isolation, and test data modules.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Major Interfaces</title>
        <para>
          The hybrid-electric architecture has controlled interfaces with the
          aircraft electrical power system, propulsion control system, cockpit
          indication and recording systems, central maintenance system, thermal
          management system, ground support equipment, and applicable aircraft
          safety and protection functions.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Operating Mode Architecture</title>
        <para>
          The architecture supports normal, monitored, limited, degraded, and
          safe-state operating modes. Mode transition conditions, protective
          thresholds, flight crew indications, dispatch effects, and maintenance
          consequences shall be specified in the applicable control, operational,
          fault isolation, and maintenance data modules.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Degraded-Mode Philosophy</title>
        <para>
          The degraded-mode architecture shall prevent single equipment faults
          from causing uncontrolled propagation across propulsion, electrical,
          thermal, or control boundaries. Fault containment, isolation,
          monitoring, and maintenance reporting provisions shall be validated
          against the applicable system safety and certification baseline.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Traceability Context</title>
        <para>
          This data module belongs to the ATLAS 070-079 Propulsion Eco-Tech and
          Hybrid-Electric branch. It supports deterministic traceability between
          architecture definition, system interface definition, S1000D CSDB
          publication artefacts, verification evidence, and lifecycle governance
          records.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

      <levelledPara>
        <title>Authoring Status</title>
        <para>
          This issue is an unverified scaffold. The content shall be completed,
          reviewed, and validated against the applicable BREX data module,
          business rules, applicability model, terminology rules, programme
          configuration baseline, and safety assessment evidence before CSDB
          release.
        </para>
      </levelledPara>

    </description>
  </content>

</dmodule>e>
